There's a great big elephant in the room called the economy.
هنا فيل كبير جداً فى الغرفة يسمى الإقتصاد .
So let's start talking about that.
لذا دعونا نتحدث عن ذلك .
I wanted to give you a current picture of the economy.
كنت أود أن أعطيكم صورة حالية للإقتصاد .
That's what I have behind myself.
الشئ الذى أنا بصدده هنا .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
But of course what we have to remember is this.
لكن بالطبع الذى لابد من تذكره هو هذا .
And what you have to think about is,
والذى لابد لكم من أن تفكروا به ,
when you're dancing in the flames, what's next?
عندما ترقصون فى النيران ( تتحركون فى غضب ) , ماذا بعد ؟
So what I'm going to try to do in the next 17 and a half minutes
لذلك الذى سأحاول عمله فى ال17 دقيقة ونصف القادمة
is I'm going to talk first about the flames --
هو أننى سأتحدث أولاً عن النيران --
where we are in the economy --
أين موقعنا فى الإقتصاد --
and then I'm going to take three trends
وعندها سأخذ ثلاثة إتجاهات
that have taken place at TED over the last 25 years
حدثت فى تيد عبر الخمسة وعشرون عاماً الأخيرة
and that will take place in this conference
و ستحدث فى هذا المؤتمر
and I will try and bring them together.
وسأحاول أن اربطهم معاً .
And I will try and give you a sense of what the ultimate reboot looks like.
وسأحاول أن أعطيكم مشهد عن كيف يبدو أهم تغيير .
Those three trends are
تلك الإتجاهات الثلاثة هى
the ability to engineer cells,
القدرة على هندسة الخلايا ,
the ability to engineer tissues,
القدرة على هندسة الأنسجة
and robots.
والروبوت .
And somehow it will all make sense.
وعلى نحو ما سوف تصبح ذات معني.
But anyway, let's start with the economy.
لكن على أى الأحوال , دعونا نبدأ مع الإقتصاد .
There's a couple of really big problems that are still sitting there.
هناك مشكلتين يعتبروا الأكبر مازالوا على حالهما .
One is leverage.
واحدة هى قيمة الشركة والأموال التى تدين ها .
And the problem with leverage is
والمشكلة مع القيمة هى
it makes the U.S. financial system look like this.
أنها تجعل النظام الإقتصادى الأمريكى يبدو كهذا .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
So, a normal commercial bank has nine to 10 times leverage.
لذا , أى بنك تجارى عادى به نسبة 9/10 من القيمة .
That means for every dollar you deposit, it loans out about nine or 10.
هذا يعنى أنه لكل دولار تودعوه يكْون قرض 9 أو 10 .
A normal investment bank is not a deposit bank,
أى بنك إستثمارى لا يع بنك توفير ,
it's an investment bank;
إنه بنك إستثمارى :
it has 15 to 20 times.
به 15 - 20 مرة .
It turns out that B of A in September had 32 times.
إنه ينتج رقم س من ص فى سبتمبر كان له 32 مرة .
And your friendly Citibank had 47 times.
وصديقكم سيتى بنك له 47 مرة .
Oops.
أوبس .
That means every bad loan goes bad 47 times over.
ذلك يعنى أنه كل قرض سيء يكوْن 47 مرة أسوأ .
And that, of course, is the reason why all of you
وذلك , بالطبع , هو السبب لماذا كلكم
are making such generous and wonderful donations
تقدمون تبرعات مذهلة وكريمة
to these nice folks.
إلى هؤلاء الأشخاص اللطاف .
And as you think about that,
وكما تفكرون خلال ذلك ,
you've got to wonder: so what do banks have in store for you now?
لابد لكم من أن تتعجبوا : ماذا لدى البنوك الآن فى مخازنها لكم ؟
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
It ain't pretty.
ليس بالشيء الجميل .
The government, meanwhile, has been acting like Santa Claus.
الحكومة , منذ فترة , وهى تتصرف مثل سانتا كلوز ( بابا نويل ).
We all love Santa Claus, right?
كلنا نحب سانتا كلوز , صحيح ؟
But the problem with Santa Clause is,
لكن المشكلة مع سانتا كلوز هى ,
if you look at the mandatory spending of what these folks have been doing
لو نظرتم إلى المصروفات الإلزامية لهذه البنوك وكيفية صرفها منذ فترة ,
and promising folks,
ووعودهم لنا ,
it turned out that in 1967, 38 percent was mandatory spending
إنها تنتج كما حدث فى 1967 , نسبة 38 كانت مصروفات إلزامية
on what we call "entitlements."
على ما نسمية " الإستحقاقات ."
And then by 2007 it was 68 percent.
وفى عام 2007 كانت النسبة 68 .
And we weren't supposed to run into 100 percent until about 2030.
ولم يكن من المفترض وقتها أن نصل إلى نسبة 100% ليس قبل عام 2030 .
Except we've been so busy giving away a trillion here, a trillion there,
فيما عدا أننا كنا مشغولين بالتخلى عن تريليون دولار هنا , تريليون دولار هناك ,
that we've brought that date of reckoning forward
كنا مشغولين بأن نؤجل هذه الحسابات إلى تاريخ
to about 2017.
حوالى 2017 .
And we thought we were going to be able to lay these debts off on our kids,
وإعتقدنا أننا كنا قادرين على إزاحة هذه الديون على أبنائنا ,
but, guess what?
لكن , خمنوا ماذا ؟
We're going to start to pay them.
نحن سندفعهم بالكامل .
And the problem with this stuff is, now that the bill's come due,
والمشكلة مع هذه الطريقة هى , أن الفاتورة واجب تسديدها الأن ,
it turns out Santa isn't quite as cute when it's summertime.
مما جعل سانتا يبدو ليس باللطف المعتاد عندما يأتى الصيف .
Right?
مضبوط ؟
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Here's some advice from one of the largest investors in the United States.
هنا بعض النصائح من واحد من أكبر المستثمرين فى الولايات المتحدة .
This guy runs the China Investment Corporation.
الذى يدير شركة إستثمار صينية .
He is the main buyer of U.S. Treasury bonds.
إنه المشترى الرئيسى لسندات الخزانة الأمريكية .
And he gave an interview in December.
وقد أعطى مقابلة فى ديسمبر .
Here's his first bit of advice.
هنا أول وأبسط نصيحة .
And here's his second bit of advice.
وهنا ثانى جزء من نصائحه .
And, by the way,
وبالمناسبة ,
the Chinese Prime Minister reiterated this at Davos last Sunday.
رئيس الوزراء الصينى كررها مجدداً فى مؤتمر دافوس الأحد الماضى .
This stuff is getting serious enough
هذه المشكلة باتت خطيرة بما يكفى .
that if we don't start paying attention to the deficit,
إذا لم نبدأ بالإنتباه إلى العجز ,
we're going to end up losing the dollar.
سننتهى إلى فقدان الدولار .
And then all bets are off.
وعندها كل الرهانات ستنتهى .
Let me show you what it looks like.
دعونى أريكم كيف تبدو .
I think I can safely say
أعتقد أننى أستطيع أن أقول بأمان
that I'm the only trillionaire in this room.
أننى التريليونير الوحيد فى هذه الغرفة .
This is an actual bill.
هذه ورقة مالية حقيقة .
And it's 10 triliion dollars.
وهى عشرة تريليونات من الدولارات .
The only problem with this bill is it's not really worth very much.
المشكلة الوحيدة بهذه الورقة المالية هى إنها بالفعل لا تساوى الكثير .
That was eight bucks last week, four bucks this week,
إنها كانت تساوى 8 دولارات الأسبوع الماضى , أربعة دولارات هذا الأسبوع ,
a buck next week.
دولار واحد الأسبوع القادم .
And that's what happens to currencies when you don't stand behind them.
وهذا ما يحدث للعملات عندما لا تقفوا بجانبها وتدعموها .
So the next time somebody as cute as this shows up on your doorstep,
لذا المرة القادمة عندما يطرق بابك شخص ظريف مثل هذا ,
and sometimes this creature's called Chrysler and sometimes Ford and sometimes ... whatever you want --
وأحياناً ذلك الكائن يسمى كرايسلر وأحياناً فورد و أحياناً أى إسم آخر --
you've just got to say no.
لابد لك من أن تقول لا .
And you've got to start banishing a word that's called "entitlement."
ولابد لك من تبدأ فى التخلص من كلمة تُسمى " الإستحقاقات ."
And the reason we have to do that in the short term
وهناك سبب يجعلنا من أن نفعل ذلك على المدى القصير
is because we have just run out of cash.
ألا وهو أننا على وشك أن ننتهى من الأموال السائلة .
If you look at the federal budget, this is what it looks like.
إذا نظرتم إلى الميزانية الفيدرالية , هكذا تبدو .
The orange slice is what's discretionary.
قطعة البرتقال هى ما نحن أحرار فيه .
Everything else is mandated.
كل شيء أخر نحن ملزمين به .
It makes no difference if we cut out the bridges to Alaska in the overall scheme of things.
لا فرق إذا قطعنا الكبارى إلى ألاسكا فى الخطة الشاملة للتخطيط .
So what we have to start thinking about doing
لذلك الذى علينا فعله هو أن نبدأ التفكير بعمل
is capping our medical spending
حدود للمصروفات فى الميدان الطبى
because that's a monster that's simply going to eat the entire budget.
لأن ذلك هو الوحش الذى ببساطة سوف يأكل الميزانية بأكملها .
We've got to start thinking about asking people
لابد أن نبدأ التفكير بسؤال الناس
to retire a little bit later.
للخروج إلى سن المعاش متأخراً قليلاً .
If you're 60 to 65 you retire on time.
لو إنك 60 - 65 فهذا سن سليم للتقاعد .
Your 401(k) just got nailed.
نظام الإستثمار فى المعاشات مقبوض عليه .
If you're 50 to 60 we want you to work two years more.
لو إنك 50 - 60 نريدك أن تعمل سنتين زيادة .
If you're under 50 we want you to work four more years.
لو إنك أقل من 50 عاماً نريدك أن تعمل أربعة سنوات زيادة .
The reason why that's reasonable is,
السبب فى أن ذلك شيء عقلانى جداً هو ,
when your grandparents were given Social Security,
عندما أُعطيت مزايا الرقم القومى لأجدادكم ,
they got it at 65 and were expected to check out at 68.
فإنهما أخذوها فى سن 65 وكان من المتوقع أن يرحلوا فى سن 68 .
Sixty-eight is young today.
68 هو سن صغير اليوم .
We've also got to cut the military about three percent a year.
لابد لنا أيضاً من خصم نسبة 3% من ميزانية الدفاع كل عام .
We've got to limit other mandatory spending.
لابد من تحجيم المصروفات الضرورية الأخرى .
We've got to quit borrowing as much,
يلزمنا أن نكف عن الإستدانة بكثرة
because otherwise the interest is going to eat that whole pie.
لأنه من ناحية أخرى فائدة القروض سوف تأكل الكعكة كلها .
And we've got to end up with a smaller government.
وسينتهى بنا الحال إلى حكومة أصغر .
And if we don't start changing this trend line,
وإذا لم نبدأ فى تغيير هذه النزعة ,
we are going to lose the dollar
سنفقد الدولار
and start to look like Iceland.
وسنبدأ فى الظهور مثل أيسلندا .
I got what you're thinking.
أعرف فيما تفكرون .
This is going to happen when hell freezes over.
هذا سيحدث عندما يتجمد الجحيم كله .
But let me remind you this December it did snow in Vegas.
لكن دعونى أذكركم أنه هطلت ثلوج فى لاس فيجاس فى ديسمبر .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
Here's what happens if you don't address this stuff.
هذا ما سيحدث لو لم نتمكن من معالجة هذه المشكلة .
So, Japan had a fiscal real estate crisis
اليابان , كان بها أزمة عقارية مالية
back in the late '80s.
فى أواخر الثمانينات .
And its 225 largest companies today
وشركاتها الـ 225 من أكبر الشركات اليوم
are worth one quarter of what they were 18 years ago.
قيمتها تعادل ربع ما كانت عليه منذ 18 عاماً .
We don't fix this now,
لو لم نصلح هذا اليوم ,
how would you like to see a Dow 3,500 in 2026?
ما رأيكم أن تروا مؤشر داو 3,500 فى 2026 ؟
Because that's the consequence of not dealing with this stuff.
لأن هذه هى النتائج اللاحقة لعدم تعاملنا مع هذه المشكلة .
And unless you want this person
وما لم تريدوا هذا الشخص
to not just become the CFO of Florida, but the United States,
ليس فقط ليكون رئيس الإدارة المالية لولاية فلوريدا , لكن لكل الولايات المتحدة ,
we'd better deal with this stuff.
سوف نتعامل بطريقة أفضل مع هذه المشكلة .
That's the short term. That's the flame part.
هذا على المدى القصير . ذلك الجزء المشتعل .
That's the financial crisis.
هذه الأزمة المالية .
Now, right behind the financial crisis there's a second and bigger wave
الأن , بعد الأزمة المالية بالضبط هناك موجة ثانية أكبر
that we need to talk about.
نحتاج أن نتحدث عنها .
That wave is much larger, much more powerful,
تلك الموجة أكبر بكثير , أكثر قوة ,
and that's of course the wave of technology.
وتلك بالطبع هى موجة التكنولوجيا .
And what's really important in this stuff is,
وما يهم بالحقيقة فى هذه المشكلة هو ,
as we cut, we also have to grow.
كما خفضنا , لابد من أننا ننمو أيضاً .
Among other things, because startup companies
خلال بعض الأشياء الأخرى , لأن الشركات الحديثة
are .02 percent of U.S. GDP investmentm
تكوْن نسبة 0.2 من إجمالى الدخل العام للإستثمارات
and they're about 17.8 percent of output.
وتكوْن حوالى 17,8% من الناتج كله .
It's groups like that in this room that generate the future of the U.S. economy.
إنها مجموعات مثل التى هنا فى هذه الغرفة التى تولد مستقبل الإقتصاد الأمريكى .
And that's what we've got to keep growing.
وهذه هى الطريقة التى لابد لنا أن ننمو بها .
We don't have to keep growing these bridges to nowhere.
ليس أن نمد هذه الكبارى إلى لامكان .
So let's bring a romance novelist into this conversation.
لذا دعونا نحضر كاتب قصص رومانسية لهذه المحادثة .
And that's where these three trends come together.
وهذا حيث تتقابل تلك الثلاث ظواهر تأتى معاً .
That's where the ability to engineer microbes,
حيث القدرة على هندسة الميكروبات ,
the ability to engineer tissues,
القدرة على هندسة الأنسجة الحيوية ,
and the ability to engineer robots
والقدرة على هندسة الإنسان الألى
begin to lead to a reboot.
بدأت تقود إلى بدايات تغيير ما .
And let me recap some of the stuff you've seen.
ودعونى أن أكرر بعض النقاط التى رأيتمونها .
Craig Venter showed up last year
كريج فينتر ظهر لنا العام الماضى
and showed you the first fully programmable cell that acts like hardware
وأوضح لكم أول خلية كاملة البرمجة التى يمكن أن تعمل كأجزاء كمبيوتر
where you can insert DNA and have it boot up as a different species.
حيث يمكنكم إدخال DNA ويبدأ الكمبيوتر العمل كأنواع مختلفة .
In parallel, the folks at MIT
فى نفس المجال , الناس فى معهد ماساتشوستس للتقنية
have been building a standard registry of biological parts.
يعملون على بناء وجمع الأجزاء الجينية للأجزاء الحيوية .
So think of it as a Radio Shack for biology.
لذا يمكنكم أن تعتبروا البيولوجى كمحلات راديو شاك .
You can go out and get your proteins, your RNA, your DNA, whatever.
يمكنكم أن تخرجوا و تشتروا بروتينكم , RNA الحمض الريبى النووى , DNA الحمض النووى , وغيرهم .
And start building stuff.
وتبدأون بناء أشياء .
In 2006 they brought together high school students and college students
فى 2006 أحضروا طلاب من مدارس الثانوى وطلاب جامعيين
and started to build these little odd creatures.
وبدأوا فى بناء هذه المخلوقات الغريبة الصغيرة .
They just happened to be alive instead of circuit boards.
حدث بالصدفة أنه كان على قيد الحياه بالإضافة إلى مجموعة الأسلاك الكهربية .
Here was one of the first things they built.
هنا واحد من هذه الأشياء التى بنوها .
So, cells have this cycle.
لذا , الخلايا لها هذه الخصائص الدورية .
First they don't grow.
أولا إنها لا تنمو .
Then they grow exponentially.
إنها تنمو بطريقة مضطردة ( أسية ) .
Then they stop growing.
بعدها توقف النمو .
Graduate students wanted a way of telling which stage they were in.
طلاب الدراسات العليا أرادوا أن يعلنوا فى أى مرحلة وقفوا عندها .
So they engineered these cells
إنهم عملوا على هندسة هذه الخلايا
so that when they're growing in the exponential phase,
حيث عندما تنموا بالطريقة الأسية ,
they would smell like wintergreen.
فإن رائحتهم تبدو مثل نبات الوينترجرين .
And when they stopped growing they would smell like bananas.
وعندما تبدأ فى التوقف عن النمو فإن رائحتها تبدو مثل الموز .
And you could tell very easily when your experiment was working
وتستطيعون أن تعرفوا عندما تجربتكم تنجح بسهولة
and wasn't, and where it was in the phase.
وعندما لا تنجح , وأين تكون فى مراحل نموها .
This got a bit more complicated two years later.
هذه التجربة أصبحت أكثر تعقيداً أخر عامين .
Twenty-one countries came together. Dozens of teams.
21 دولة جاءت معاً . العديد من الفرق .
They started competing.
بدأوا المنافسة .
The team from Rice University started to engineer the substance in red wine
فريق من جامعة رايس بدأ بهندسة مادة معينة فى النبيذ الأحمر
that makes red wine good for you
يجعل النبيذ الأحمر صحياً أكثر لجسدك
into beer.
من البيرة .
So you take resveratrol and you put it into beer.
إذا أخذت المركب " ريسفيراترول " الكيميائى ووضعته فى البيرة .
Of course, one of the judges is wandering by, and he goes,
بالطبع , أحد القضاة مُتعجب , يقول ,
"Wow! Cancer-fighting beer! There is a God."
" أوه ! السرطان يقاتل البيرة ! هناك إعجاز . "
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
The team from Taiwan was a little bit more ambitious.
فريق من تايوان كان أكثر طموحاً .
They tried to engineer bacterias in such a way
فقد حاولوا أن يعالجوا البكتيريا بطريقة معينة
that they would act as your kidneys.
حيث أنها تتصرف كالكلى الطبيعية فى الجسم .
Four years ago, I showed you this picture.
منذ أربعة سنوات مضت , أوضحت لكم هذه الصورة .
And people oohed and ahhed,
والناس تعجبت لدرجة الذهول ,
because Cliff Tabin had been able to grow an extra wing on a chicken.
لأن كليف تابين ( عالم أحياء ) كان قادراً على أن يُنمى جناح زائد فى الدجاجة .
And that was very cool stuff back then.
وذلك كان شيئاً ظريفاً وقتها .
But now moving from bacterial engineering to tissue engineering,
ولكن الأن بالتحرك من هندسة البكتيريا إلى هندسة النسج ,
let me show you what's happened in that period of time.
دعونى أريكم ماذا يحدث فى تلك الفترة الزمنية
Two years ago, you saw this creature.
منذ عامين , رأيتم هذا الكائن .
An almost-extinct animal from Xochimilco, Mexico
حيوان من إكسوشيميلكو ,بالمكسيك تقريباً إنقرض
called an axolotl
يسمى أوكسولوتل
that can re-generate its limbs.
يستطيع أن يعيد تكوين أجزاءه مرة أخرى .
You can freeze half its heart. It regrows.
يمكنكم تجميد نصف قلبه . إنه يعيد تكوين نفسه .
You can freeze half the brain. It regrows.
يمكنكم تجميد نصف عقله . إنه يعيد تكوين نفسه .
It's almost like leaving Congress.
إنه تقريباً مثل ترك الكونجرس .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
But now, you don't have to have the animal itself to regenerate,
لكن الأن , لستم مضطريين لأن تملكون الحيوان نفسه لإعادة تكوينه ,
because you can build cloned mice molars in Petri dishes.
لأنكم تستطيعون بناء ضروس الفأر المستنسخة فى أوانى خاصة .
And, of course if you can build mice molars in Petri dishes,
و, بالطبع إذا إستطيعتم بناء ضروس الفأر المستنسخة فى أوانى خاصة ,
you can grow human molars in Petri dishes.
تستطيعون عمل نفس الشيئ مع ضروس البشر فى أوانى خاصة .
This should not surprise you, right?
ليس من المفترض أن يفاجئكم هذا , مضبوط ؟
I mean, you're born with no teeth.
أقصد , قد ولدتم بدون أسنان .
You give away all your teeth to the tooth fairy.
تبدلون كل أسنانكم خلال عملية التبديل التى تحدث فى الصغر .
You re-grow a set of teeth.
تنمو مجموعة أسنان جديدة .
But then if you lose one of those second set of teeth, they don't regrow,
لكن عندما تفقدون واحدة من المجموعة التى تنمو فى المرة الثانية , لا تنمو بديل لها ,
unless, if you're a lawyer.
إلا فى حالة واحدة , لو أنت محامى .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
But, of course, for most of us,
لكن , بالطبع , فى الغالبية منا ,
we know how to grow teeth, and therefore we can take adult stem teeth,
نحن نعرف كيفية نمو الأسنان , وتبعاً لذلك نستطيع أن نأخذ أسنان شخص بالغ ,
put them on a biodegradable mold, re-grow a tooth,
ووضعها فى أوانى ذات محفزات خاصة , ثم إعادة نمو الأسنان ,
and simply implant it.
وببساطة زرعها .
And we can do it with other things.
ونستطيع عمل ذلك مع أشياء أخرى .
So, a Spanish woman who was dying of T.B. had a donor trachea,
لذا , إمرأة أسبانية كانت تموت من الدرن كانت قد بدلت قصبتها الهوائية ,
they took all the cells off the trachea,
إنهم صمموا خلايا مشابهه لكل خلايا القصبة الهوائية خارجاً ,
they spraypainted her stem cells onto that cartilage.
رشوا خلاياها الجذعية لربطها بالغضروف الجديد .
She regrew her own trachea,
قصبة هوائية جديدة كانت قد نمت ,
and 72 hours later it was implanted.
قد زرعت فى خلال 72 ساعة بعد ذلك .
She's now running around with her kids.
هى الآن تجرى مع أطفالها .
This is going on in Tony Atala's lab in Wake Forest
يجرى هذا فى معمل تونى عاطالله فى واك فوريست
where he is re-growing ears for injured soldiers,
حيث يعالج بإعادة نمو أذان الجنود الجرحى ,
and he's also re-growing bladders.
وهو أيضاً يعالج بإعادة نمو المثانة .
So there are now nine women walking around Boston
هناك الأن تسعة سيدات يسيرون فى مدينة بوسطن
with re-grown bladders,
بمثانات جديدة مزروعة ,
which is much more pleasant than walking around with a whole bunch of plastic bags
الشيء المُفرح أكثر كثيراً من السير بمجموعة أكياس بلاستيكية
for the rest of your life.
لباقية العمر .
This is kind of getting boring, right?
هذا الحديث بدأ أن يكون مملاُ بعض الشيء , صح ؟
I mean, you understand where this story's going.
أقصد , أنتم تفهمون إلى أين تذهب بنا هذه القصة .
But, I mean it gets more interesting.
لكن , أقصد أنها فى طريقها لأن تكون مثيرة .
Last year, this group was able to take all the cells off a heart,
العام الماضى , هذه المجموعة كانت قادرة لأن تصمم خلايا مشابهة لكل خلايا القلب ,
leaving just the cartilage.
تاركين فقط الخلايا الغضروفية .
Then, they sprayed stem cells onto that heart, from a mouse.
عندها , رشوا الخلايا الجذعية لهذا القلب , من فأر .
Those stem cells self-organized, and that heart started to beat.
تلك الخلابا الجذعية منظمة تنظيم ذاتى , وذلك القلب بدأ فى الدق .
Life happens.
الحياة تحدث .
This may be one of the ultimate papers.
من المحتمل أن يكون من أهم الأوراق .
This was done in Japan and in the U.S., published at the same time,
تم هذا فى اليابان وفى الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية , نُشرت فى نفس الوقت ,
and it rebooted skin cells into stem cells, last year.
وبدأ فى تحويل الخلايا الجلدية إلى خلايا جذعية , العام الماضى .
That meant that you can take the stuff right here,
ذلك يعنى أنه يمكنكم أخذ الأشياء من هنا ,
and turn it into almost anything in your body.
وتحويلها إلى أى شيء تقريباً فى جسدك .
And this is becoming common, it's moving very quickly,
وهذا قد أصبح معتاد , وتتحرك بسرعة كبيرة ,
it's moving in a whole series of places.
إنها تتحرك فى سلسلة كاملة من الأماكن .
Third trend: robots.
الظاهرة الثالثة : الإنسان الآلى .
Those of us of a certain age grew up expecting that by now
هؤلاء منا الذين فى سن معينة قد شبوا متوقعين ذلك الآن
we would have Rosie the Robot from "The Jetsons" in our house.
سيكون لدينا روز الإنسان الآلى من " الجيتسونس" فى منزلنا .
And all we've got is a Roomba.
وكل ما لدينا "رومبا " ( مكنسة آلية كهربائية ) .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
We also thought we'd have this robot to warn us of danger.
كنا نظن أيضاً أن هذه الألة يمكن أن تحذرنا من الخطر .
Didn't happen.
هذا لم يحدث .
And these were robots engineered for a flat world, right?
وهذه الألات قد صُممت من أجل عالم ثابت غير متغير , صحيح ؟
So, Rosie runs around on skates
لذا , روز تتحرك بواسطة أرجل خاصة
and the other one ran on flat threads.
بينما الأخر كانت تتحرك على بكر أو عجل مُسطح .
If you don't have a flat world, that's not good,
لو أنكم لا تعيشون فى عالم ثابت , فإن ذلك لا يكون جيد ,
which is why the robot's we're designing today are a little different.
ذلك يبين لماذا الروبوت الذى نصممه اليوم هو مختلف بعض الشيئ .
This is Boston Dynamics' "BigDog."
هذه هى " بيج دوج " من بوستن دايناميكس ( إنسان آلى من تصنيع أمريكى )
And this is about as close as you can get to a physical Turing test.
وهذا هو أقرب ما يمكنكم الحصول عليه لإختبار ذكاء الأله .
O.K., so let me remind you, a Turing test is where you've got a wall,
حسناً , دعونى أذكركم , إختبار ذكاء الأله هو عندما يكون لديكم حائط ,
you're talking to somebody on the other side of the wall,
تتحدثون إلى شخص آخر فى الناحية الأخرى من الحائط ,
and when you don't know if that thing is human or animal --
وعندما لا تعرفون إذا كان ذلك الشيء هو إنسان أم حيوان --
that's when computers have reached human intelligence.
فهذا هو عندما تصل الكمبيوترات إلى مستوى الذكاء البشرى .
This is not an intelligence Turing rest,
هذا لا يعتبر إختبار ذكاء للألة ,
but this is as close as you can get to a physical Turing test.
لكن هذا هو أقرب ما يمكنكم الحصول عليه للوصول إلى إختبار الذكاء الفيزيائى للألة .
And this stuff is moving very quickly,
وهذه الأشياء تتقدم بسرعة كبيرة ,
and by the way, that thing can carry about 350 pounds of weight.
وبالمناسبة , ذلك الشيء يستطيع أن يحمل ثقل حوالى 350 باوند .
These are not the only interesting robots.
هذه ليست فقط الروبوت المثيرة .
You've also got flies, the size of flies,
عندكم أيضاً الحشرات الطائرة , فى حجم الحشرات الطائرة ,
that are being made by Robert Wood at Harvard.
التى صُنعت بواسطة روبرت وود فى هارفارد .
You've got Stickybots that are being made at Stanford.
عندكم ستكيبوتس التى صُنعت فى ستانفورد .
And as you bring these things together,
وبتجميعكم لهذه الأشياء معاً ,
as you bring cells, biological tissue engineering and mechanics together,
مثل تجميع التليفونات المحمولة , هندسة الأنسجة البيولوجية والميكانيكية معاً .
you begin to get some really odd questions.
تبدأون فى التفكير فى أسئلة هى غريبة بالفعل .
In the last Olympics, this gentleman,
فى أخر أولومبياد , هذا الرجل ,
who had several world records in the Special Olympics,
الذى حقق أرقام قياسية عديدة فى الأولومبياد الخاصة بالمعاقين ,
tried to run in the normal Olympics.
حاول أن يعدو فى الأولومبياد العادية .
The only issue with Oscar Pistorius
المشكلة الوحيدة مع أوسكار بيستوروس
is he was born without bones in the lower part of his legs.
أنه قد وُلد بدون عِظام فى الجزء الأسفل من أرجله .
He came within about a second of qualifying.
قد جاء ترتيبه الثانى فى التصنيفات .
He sued to be allowed to run,
قد رُفعت عليه قضية بسبب السماح له بالعدو ,
and he won the suit,
وقد فاز بالقضية ,
but didn't qualify by time.
إلا أنه لم يتأهل فى الوقت المناسب .
Next Olympics, you can bet that Oscar, or one of Oscar's successors,
فى الأولومبياد القادمة , تستطيعون أن تراهنوا على أن أوسكار , أو أحد أتباعه الناجحين ,
is going to make the time.
سوف يحقق الزمن المطلوب .
And two or three Olympics after that, they are going to be unbeatable.
وإثنين أو ثلاثة أولومبياد بعد ذلك , سوف لا يمكن هزيمتهم أبداً .
And as you bring these trends together, and as you think of what it means
وبمقارنة هذه الظواهر معاً , وبالتفكير ماذا تعنى
to take people who are profoundly deaf, who can now begin to hear --
أن تجعل الناس الذين يعانون صمّ بشدة , الذين بدؤا يستطيعون أن يسمعوا --
I mean, remember the evolution of hearing aids, right?
أقصد , تذكروا ثورة تطور السمع , صحيح ؟
I mean, your grandparents had these great big cones,
أقصد , أجدادكم كان لهم هذه الأشكال المخروطية الكبيرة ,
and then your parents had these odd boxes
وبعدها أبائكم كان لهم تلك الصناديق الغريبة
that would squawk at odd times during dinner,
التى تقعقع أصوات فى أوقات غريبة أثناء العشاء ,
and now we have these little buds that nobody sees.
والآن عندنا هذه البراعم الصغيرة التى لا يراها أحد .
And now you have cochlear implants
والآن عندكم زراعة كوشلير ( جهاز للناس التى تعانى عدم سماع كامل )
that go into people's heads and allow the deaf to begin to hear.
التى تدخل فى دماغ الناس وتسمح للشخص أن يبدأ فى السمع .
Now, they can't hear as well as you and I can.
الآن , إنهم يستطيعون أن يسمعوا مثلكم ومثلما أستطيع .
But, in 10 or 15 machine generations they will,
لكن , فى خلال 10 أو 15 جيل للماكينات فإنهم سوف ,
and these are machine generations, not human generations.
وهذه الأجيال الألية , ليست أجيال من البشر .
And about two or three years after they can hear as well as you and I can,
وفى خلال إثنين أو ثلاثة أعوام بعد أن يستطيعوا السماع جيداً مثلكم ومثلى ,
they'll be able to hear maybe how bats sing, or how whales talk,
إنهم ربما سوف يكونوا قادرين أن يسمعوا غناء الخفافيش , أو حديث الحيتان ,
or how dogs talk, and other types of tonal scales.
أو كيف يتحدث الكلاب , أو الأنواع الأخرى من تدرج الأنغام .
They'll be able to focus their hearing,
سوف يكونوا قادرين أن يركزوا سمعهم ,
they'll be able to increase the sensitivity, decrease the sensitivity,
سوف يكونوا قادرين أن يزيدوا من حساسية السمع أو خفضها ,
do a series of things that we can't do.
عمل سلسلة من الأشياء التى لا نستطيع نحن أن نعملها .
And the same thing is happening in eyes.
ونفس الشيء يحدث فى العيون .
This is a group in Germany that's beginning to engineer eyes
هذه مجموعة فى ألمانيا بدأت فى هندسة عيون
so that people who are blind can begin to see light and dark.
حيث أن الناس الذين لا يبصروا يستطيعوا أن يبدأوا فى رؤية الضوء والظلام .
Very primitive.
شيء بدائى جداً .
And then they'll be able to see shape.
وعندها سوف يكونوا قادرين أن يروا أشكال .
And then they'll be able to see color, and then they'll be able to see in definition,
وعندها سوف يكونوا قادرين أن يروا اللون , وبعدها سوف يكونوا قادرين أن يروا فى وضوح ,
and one day, they'll see as well as you and I can.
وفى يوم ما , سوف يكونوا قادرين أن يروا مثلكم ومثلى .
And a couple of years after that, they'll be able to see in ultraviolet,
وبعد ذلك ببضعة أعوام , سوف يكونوا قادرين أن يروا فى الأشعة الفوق بنفسجية ,
they'll be able to see in infrared, they'll be able to focus their eyes,
سوف يكونوا قادرين أن يروا فى الأشعة تحت الحمراء , سوف يكونوا قادرين أن يركزوا أعينهم ,
they'll be able to come into a microfocus.
سوف يكونوا قادرين أن يبتكروا نوع جديد من أشعات x .
They'll do stuff you and I can't do.
سوف يكونوا قادرين على عمل أشياء لا نستطيع أن نعملها .
All of these things are coming together,
كل هذه الأشياء متحدة معاً ,
and it's a particularly important thing to understand,
وهى شيء محدد مهم أن نفهمه ,
as we worry about the flames of the present,
كما أننا قلقين بمشاكل الحاضر ,
to keep an eye on the future.
لملاحظة ما يحدث فى المستقبل .
And, of course, the future is looking back 200 years,
وبالطبع ,المستقبل ينظر للوراء 200 عاماً مضت ,
because next week is the 200th anniversary of Darwin's birth.
لأن الأسبوع المُقبل يوافق ذكرى ميلاد داروين المائتين .
And it's the 150th anniversary of the publication of "The Origin of Species."
وأيضاً الذكرى 150 لنشر كتاب " أصل الأنواع " .
And Darwin, of course, argued that evolution is a natural state.
وداروين بالطبع , إدعى أن التطور هو حاله طبيعية .
It is a natural state in everything that is alive, including hominids.
إنه حاله طبيعية فى كل شيء حى , بما فيهم القردة الأوائل .
There have actually been 22 species of hominids
هناك بالفعل 22 نوع من القردة الأوائل
that have been around, have evolved, have wandered in different places,
موجوديين فى الطبيعة , قد تطورت ,تجولت فى أماكن مختلفة ,
have gone extinct.
قد إنقرضت تماماً .
It is common for hominids to evolve.
من الطبيعى للقردة القدامى أن تتطور .
And that's the reason why, as you look at the hominid fossil record,
وذلك هو السبب لماذا , كما تنظرون إلى سجلات الحفريات الأدمية ,
erectus, and heidelbergensis, and floresiensis, and Neanderthals,
مجموعات الإنسان المنتصب , وإنسان هايدلبيرغ , إنسان فلويس , والنيانتردال ,
and Homo sapiens, all overlap.
والإنسان بإسمه العلمى , كلهم متداخلون معاً .
The common state of affairs is to have overlapping versions of hominids,
الحالة المشتركة للوجود هى أن يكون هناك تداخل بين صور القردة القدامى ,
not one.
ليست واحدة .
And as you think of the implications of that,
وكما تعتقدون أنه من آثار ذلك ,
here's a brief history of the universe.
هنا ملخص تاريخى للجنس البشرى .
The universe was created 13.7 billion years ago,
الكون قد خُلق منذ 13,7 بليون سنة ,
and then you created all the stars, and all the planets,
وبعدها خُلقت كل النجوم , وكل الكواكب ,
and all the galaxies, and all the Milky Ways.
وكل المجرات , وكل مجرات درب اللبانة .
And then you created Earth about 4.5 billion years ago,
وبعدها تكونت الأرض منذ 4,5 بليون سنة مضت ,
and then you got life about four billion years ago,
وبعدها بدأت الحياه منذ أربعة بلايين سنة مضت ,
and then you got hominids about 0.006 billion years ago,
وبعدها بدأ يظهر الإنسان الأول منذ حوالى 0,006 بليون سنة مضت ,
and then you got our version of hominids about 0.0015 billion years ago.
وبعدها تطور إلى صورتنا الطبيعية منذ 0,0015 بليون سنة مضت .
Ta-dah!
تعجب !
Maybe the reason for thr creation of the universe,
ربما يكون , السبب فى خلق الكون ,
and all the galaxies, and all the planets, and all the energy,
وكل المجرات , وكل الكواكب , وكل الطاقة ,
and all the dark energy, and all the rest of stuff
وكل الطاقة المظلمة , وكل الأشياء الأخرى
is to create what's in this room.
هو خلق ما هو موجود فى هذه الغرفة .
Maybe not.
ربما لا .
That would be a mildly arrogant viewpoint.
أقل ما يقال أن هذه رؤية مغرورة .
(Laughter)
( ضحك )
So, if that's not the purpose of the universe, then what's next?
لذلك , إذا لم يكن هذا هو السبب فى تكوين الكون , إذا ماذا بعد ؟
I think what we're going to see is we're going to see a different species of hominid.
أعتقد ما سوف نراه هو أننا سنرى نوع مختلف من أنواع القرود .
I think we're going to move from a Homo sapiens into a Homo evolutis.
أنا أعتقد أننا سننتقل من صورة الإنسان العادية إلى صورة حديثة تماماً ( لها صفات أقوى ).
And I think this isn't 1,000 years out.
وأعتقد أن هذا ليس على بُعد 1,000 قادمة .
I think most of us are going to glance at it,
أعتقد أن معظمنا سوف يلقى نظره عليها ,
and our grandchildren are going to begin to live it.
وأن أحفادنا سوف يبدأون معايشتها .
And a Homo evolutis brings together these three trends
والصورة الحديثة للإنسان هذه تُحضر لنا هذه الظواهر الثلاثة معاً
into a hominid that takes direct and deliberate control
إلى صورة من صورة القرود تتحكم وتسيطر سيطرة مقصودة
over the evolution of his species, her species and other species.
عبر تطور أنواعه , أنواعها والأنواع الأخرى .
And that, of course, would be the ultimate reboot.
وذلك , بالطبع , سوف يكون إعادة التغيير الأهم والمقصود .
Thank you very much.
أشكركم كثيراً .
(Applause)
( تصفيق )